A Guide to the Eula Allen Collection, 1932-1974
The Edgar Cayce Foundation
The Edgar Cayce Foundation
Eula Allen Collection, 1932-1974
The Edgar Cayce Foundation, Virginia Beach, Virginia
Coll. 32
3 Linear Feet 3 boxes.
Allen, Eula
Arrangement
Arranged in alphabetical order by material type.
Biographical / Historical
Eula Mildred Allen was born on May 15, 1899, to Hill Owsley and Minnie Bruse in Pomeroy, Washington. She married Harold Allen, an officer in the United States Navy, and settled in Norfolk, Virginia. Mignon Helms, an A.R.E. member and Eula's neighbor, introduced Eula to Edgar Cayce. She received several readings, including a Life reading in 1942. Eula and her husband Harold became A.R.E. members. When Harold retired from the U.S. Navy, he ran the A.R.E. Press at Virginia Beach Headquarters. Eula was chosen by lot to be a member of Study Group Number 1. While living in Norfolk, she attended Study Group meetings, Prayer Group Meetings, and Edgar Cayce's Tuesday Night Bible Class. She served on the house committee when A.R.E. was located at the former Cayce home on Arctic Crescent, and as a hostess for the A.R.E. Congress each June. She first lectured for the organization at the 1949 Congress and later became a prolific lecturer, teacher and writer. She also served on the A.R.E. Board of Trustees. During the 1960s and 1970s, she held a popular youth study group at A.R.E. headquarters. She published her 'Creation Trilogy' (Before the Beginning, River of Time, and You Are Forever) from 1963 to 1966. Allen died on March 1, 1978 in Mathews, Virginia at the age of 78.
Scope and Contents
Materials include Eula Allen's professional correspondence, research notes, writings, and collection of publications related to Edgar Cayce, the Association for Research and Enlightenment, A.R.E. study group work, the Edgar Cayce Foundation, and spiritual studies.
- Box 1
  - binder [262 readings], undated; Folder 1:1
  - binder [281 readings], undated; Folder 1:2
  - binder [A.R.E. publications], 1958-1966; Folder 1:3; A.R.E. Bulletin
  - binder [A.R.E. publications and personal notes], 1941-1961; Folder 1:4; -The Resurrection -Soul Mates -A.R.E. Bulletin, July-August 1961 -The Immaculate Conception -Reincarnation -spiritual exercise -poem: The Creation -poem, untitled -A.R.E. Bulletin and extracts, 1941-1943
  - binder [A Search for God lessons], 1935-1942; Folder 1:5
  - binder [Edgar Cayce; Egypt], 1940-1950; Folder 1:6
  - binder [Edgar Cayce Foundation Medical Research Bulletin], 1971-1973; Folder 1:7
  - binder [Edgar Cayce Readings extracts], 1945-1948; Folder 1:8
  - binder [Edgar Cayce Readings on A Search for God Book II], 1961; Folder 1:9
  - binder [Edgar Cayce Readings supplements], 1959-1963; Folder 1:10
  - binder [Individual Reference File], 1974; Folder 1:11
  - binder [Tarot; esoteric traditions], undated; Folder 1:12
  - binder [workbook: A Search For God Vol. 1], 1964; Folder 1:13; workbook used in Rebecca Hanchey's A.R.E. Summer School course.
  - binder [World Affairs book], 1959; Folder 1:14
- Box 2, A.R.E. Bulletin, 1932-1945. A Study of the Revelation, 1952. Circulating Files, 1960-1970. Eula Allen Trilogy: Before the Beginning, 1968; The River of Time 1968; You Are Forever, 1968.
- Box 3
  - A Commentary on the Book of Revelation, 1961; Folder 3:1
  - A Commentary on the Book of Revelation, 1967; Folder 3:2
  - announcement [Mysteries of the Mind Psychic Radio Program], 1938; Folder 3:3
  - articles [Biblical studies], 1940-1960; Folder 3:4; -Old Testament: Alive!, Gladys Davis Turner, 1958
  - Bible Minutes on the Book of Genesis [Study Group #8], 1940-1941; Folder 3:5
  - copies [Edgar Cayce Readings], 1932-1969; Folder 3:6-3:7
  - correspondence, 1938-1974; Folder 3:8
  - Edgar Cayce Memorial Library feasibility study and preliminary drawings, 1966; Folder 3:9
  - Edgar Cayce Palestine readings, undated; Folder 3:10
  - Edgar Cayce Readings: A Search for God Book II, 1961; Folder 3:11
  - ephemera, 1968; Folder 3:12
  - folder [Bible study], 1932; Folder 3:13
  - folder [Edgar Cayce Readings extracts], undated; Folder 3:14
  - folder [Healing Group] Helen Godfrey, 1933-1944; Folder 3:15
  - folder [References from the Edgar Cayce Readings for Summer School Session], 1954; Folder 3:16
  - folder [research notes], 1940-1969; Folder 3:17
  - folder [research notes], 1964-1969; Folder 3:18
  - folder [subconscious mind / mind collection], 1930-1960; Folder 3:19
  - illustrations [Coming of Man class], undated; Folder 3:20
  - manuscript [Council of the Seven Sages of the World], undated; Folder 3:21
  - meeting transcript [The Coming of Man class], 1955; Folder 3:22
  - newsclippings, 1970; Folder 3:23
  - newspaper [The Champlain News] U.S.S. Champlain, 1945; Folder 3:24
  - poem [The Cross], undated; Folder 3:25
  - prayers [Hannah Miller; Frances Y. Morrow], undated; Folder 3:26
  - printed matter about Mr. Cayce, 1911-1967; Folder 3:27
  - program booklet [Fifteenth Annual Congress], 1946; Folder 3:28
  - publications [A.R.E.], 1940-1966; Folder 3:29
  - publications [E.C.F.], 1949-1972; Folder 3:30; -A Sequel to the Story of Edgar Cayce, Gladys Davis, 1949. -Proceedings: A Symposium on Mind-Body Relationships in the Disease Process, Medical Research Division of the Edgar Cayce Foundation and the A.R.E. Clinic, 1972.
  - research materials [Bible], 1943-1958; Folder 3:31
  - transcript [Bible Week meditation] Albert Turner, 1967; Folder 3:32
  - vinyl records [Time Life's The Swing Era], undated; Folder 3:33
  - Weekly Extracts for Year 1944 Compiled by the Los Angeles Study Groups, Folder 3:34
  - Weekly Extracts for Year 1947 Compiled by the Los Angeles Study Groups, Folder 3:35
  - West Coast Conference Report, 1948; Folder 3:36; Sechrist, Elsie
  - workbook [sales personnel development workshop], undated; Folder 3:37